在这里，我用乐高创造了一个非常简单的机器人。它只有一个旋转关节
Here I have created a very simple robot out of Lego. It's got simply one rotational joint
或一个旋转关节。并且机器人的末端执行器位置可以遵循任何点
or one revolute joint. And the end effector position of the robot can follow any point
围绕一个圆圈如果不是特别有趣或特别有用。
around a circle if not particularly interesting or particularly useful.
我们现在感兴趣的是描述这个关节的末端执行器的姿势
What we are interested in now is to describe the pose of the end effector of this one joint
机器人。末端执行器在此处用此符号表示。我们将从早些时候回忆起来
robot. The end effector is indicated by this symbol here. We will recall from the earlier
当我们想要描述二维物体的姿势时，我们附上
lecture that when we want to describe the pose of an object in two dimensions, we attach
它的坐标框架和对象的位置由位置描述
a coordinate frame to it and the position of the object is described by the position
其中描述了坐标系的原点和对象的方向
of the origin of the coordinate frame and the orientation of the object is described
通过该坐标系与参考坐标系之间的角度。我已经指出了
by the angle between that coordinate frame and the reference coordinate frame. I've indicated
这里是轴x和y的参考坐标系。
here a reference coordinate frame with the axis x and y.
我们要做的第一件事是将坐标系旋转角度Q1。那是
The first thing we're going to do is to rotate that coordinate frame by the angle Q1. That's
我们的1自由度机器人的关节角度。所以我要应用同质转换，
the joint angle of our 1 degree freedom robot. So I'm going to apply a homogeneous transformation,
以角度Q1旋转。现在我要沿着它转换坐标框架
a rotation, by the angle Q1. And now I'm going to translate the coordinate frame along the
机器人的链接。所以我现在要在x方向上应用翻译。所以灰色
link of the robot. So I'm now going to apply a translation in the x direction. So the gray
此处显示的坐标系表示机器人的姿势。我们到达末端效应器
coordinate frame shown here represents the pose of the robot. We get to the end effector
通过旋转然后平移参考坐标系来协调框架。所有这些
coordinate frame by rotating and then translating the reference coordinate frame. All these
变换是二维的。所以我们说他们属于SE2集。那是一套
transforms are in two dimensions. So we say that they belong the set SE2. That's the set
二维中的所有翻译和旋转。
of all translations and rotations in two dimensions.
使用我们在之前的讲座中学到的知识，我可以将其扩展出来。然后我可以繁殖
Using what we learned in an earlier lecture, I can expand this out. Then I can multiply
两个矩阵在一起，我想出了一个单一的齐次变换矩阵
the two matrices together and I come up with a single homogeneous transformation matrix
它描述了末端执行器的姿势。给出了末端执行器的位置
which describes the pose of the end effector. The position of the end effector is given
通过这三个齐次变换矩阵中的这两个元素，我写了它们
by these two elements in three homogeneous transformation matrix and I've written them
在这里。我们可以看到它们描述了一组位于半径圆上的点
out here. And we can see that they describe a set of points which lie on a circle of radius
A1。
A1.
因此，末端执行器的位置是关节角度Q1和方向的函数
So the position of the end effector is a function of the joint angle Q1 and the orientation
这个矩阵给出的末端执行器的数值也是Q1的函数。所以这是
of the end effector which is given by this matrix here is also a function of Q1. So its
我们不可能独立设置机器人的位置和方向。
not possible for us to independently set the position and the orientation of the robot.
在像这样的简单机器人中，没有足够的关节或自由度。
There are just not enough joints or degrees of freedom in a simple robot like this.
我们来看看在MATLAB中这样做。我将定义几个工作区变量
Let's look at doing this in MATLAB. I'm going to define a couple of workspace variables
A1表示第一连杆的长度，Q1表示关节角度。
A1 which represents a length of the first link and Q1 which represents the joint angle.
现在为了确定末端效应器的姿势，我需要将两个相乘
Now in order to determine the end effector pose, I need to multiply together a couple
基本变换
of elementary transformations.
使用机器人工具箱更简单的方法是使用名为trchain2的函数。它计算
An easier way to do this using the robot toolbox is with the function called trchain2. It computes
同质变换链的结果。
the result of the chain of homogeneous transformations.
第一个是在第一个链轮流中，然后是一个翻译
The first one in the chain rotation by Q1 and that's followed by a translation in the
x方向，沿着链路距离A1。我只是将它表示为MATLAB中的字符串
x direction, that's along the link by a distance A1. I just represent that as a string in MATLAB
然后我传递了我感兴趣的关联角度，这是Q1，这是结果。
and then I pass in the joint angle that I'm interested in which is Q1 and here is the result.
这样做是当trchain2正在执行时，它看起来是变量A1in
What this is done is when the trchain2 is executing, it looks of the variable A1 in
工作区，它查找变量Q1作为向量的第一个元素
the workspace and it looks for the variable Q1 as being the first element of the vector
我传入了。来自工作区的A1。Q1来自传递的向量。这是数字
that I passed in. A1 from the workspace. Q1 comes from the passed vector. Here is in numeric
形成表示末端执行器姿势的3x3齐次变换矩阵
form the 3x3 homogeneous transformation matrix representing the pose of the end effector
我们简单的一个链接机器人。
of our simple one link robot.
现在我可以用符号而不是数字来做。并且这样做可以调用一些函数
Now I can do it using symbols instead of numbers. And to do that invoke some functions from
MATLAB的符号工具箱，我要说Q1是一个符号，A1是一个符号。
MATLAB’s symbolic toolbox and I’m going to say Q1 is a symbol and A1 is a symbol.
现在我要做的就是重复我之前做过的命令。
Now what I'm going to do is just repeat the command that I did previously.
我们这里所拥有的是对末端效应器姿势的象征性表现;相同
And what we had here is a symbolic representation of the pose of the end effector; the same
因为我们之前制作了幻灯片。我可以使用机器人的工具箱进行的另一个是导入
as we worked out a slide ago. Another I can do using the robotic's toolbox is to import
一个平坦的一个关节机器人的模型。我用这个函数mdl_planar1和我们这样做
a model of a plainer one joint robot. I do that with this function mdl_planar1 and we
在该工作区中创建了一个新变量;变量叫做P1。你可以看到它
created a new variable in that workspace; variable called P1. You can see that it's
类型的串行链接。它是一个机器人操纵器类型的对象。
of a serial link of type. It's a robot manipulator type object.
现在有了这个特殊的类型对象，它有很多方法。一个有趣的方法
Now with this particular type object, it's got a number of methods. An interesting method
是教方法，如果我调用它，你在这里看到的只是一个图形表示
is to teach method and if I invoke that, all you see here is a graphical representation
一个链接机器人和一个简单的示教器，这里有一个滑块。而当我调整
of a one link robot and a simple teach pendant, a single slider here. And as I adjust the
滑块我们看到机器人移动。我正在调整第一个关节角度的值。我们是什么
slider we see the robot move. I'm adjusting the value of the first joint angle. What we
这里是我调整每个关节角度时机器人末端执行器的xy坐标变化。
see here is the xy coordinate of the end effector of the robot changing as I adjust each joint angle.